Penne Laingen Yellow Ribbon Collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Penne Laingen Yellow Ribbon Collection 1979-1991
AFC 1991/017
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center Library of Congress Washington, D.C. http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.home
3 linear feet 4 boxes (containing 15 folders of manuscript material; 7 sound recordings; 63 unique graphic images; 1 videocassette; 1 computer disk; 6 artifacts)
Laingen, Penne
Laingen, L. Bruce
Parsons, Gerald E.
Collection comprises Penne Laingen's yellow ribbon marking the year her husband Bruce Laingen was held hostage in Tehran, Iran, during the Iran hostage crisis from 1979 to 1981; plus a 1991 interview with the Laingens and related documentation.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Laingen, L. Bruce, collector, interviewee.; Laingen, L. Bruce.; Laingen, Penne, collector, interviewee.; Laingen, Penne.; Parsons, Gerald E., 1940-1995, interviewer.
Organizations
American Folklife Center, collector.; Archive of Folk Culture (Library of Congress)
Subjects
Iran Hostage Crisis, 1979-1981--Personal narratives.; Persian Gulf War, 1991--United States--Anecdotes.; Ribbons--Symbolic aspects.; Ribbons--United States--Folklore.
Titles
Yellow ribbon collection, 1979-1991.
Form/Genre
Artifacts.; Interviews.; Photographs.; Posters.; Sound recordings.; Videocassettes.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research. Duplication of the collection materials may be governed by copyright and other restrictions.
Acquisition
Penne and Bruce Laingen donated their yellow ribbon to the Library of Congress on July 2, 1991. Additional materials were collected by employees of the American Folklife Center.
Bibliography
Laingen, L. Bruce. Yellow Ribbon: The Secret Journal of Bruce Laingen. Washington: Brassey's (US), 1992.
Letters of L. Bruce Laingen, 1980 (MSS6085). Forms part of the Miscellaneous Manuscripts collection in the Manuscript Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
"New Yellow Ribbon Tradition," An online presentation on the American Folklife Center web site, http://www.loc.gov/folklife/ribbons/index.html
Santino, Jack. "Apply a Ribbon Magnet to the Ole Humvee: The Yellow Ribbon Tradition Reborn." Folklife Center News, 27, no. 3, Summer 2005.
"Yellow Ribbon" subject files in the American Folklife Reading Room, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content
In 1979, Penne (Penelope) Laingen tied a yellow ribbon around a tree in front of her Bethesda, Maryland home when her husband, Bruce, was among those taken hostage in the United States Embassy in Tehran, Iran. The Laingens donated this yellow ribbon to the Library of Congress in 1991. The collection contains sound recordings and a photograph from that donation ceremony. Other recordings include an interview with Bruce and Penne Laingen conducted by American Folklife Center reference specialist, Gerald E. Parsons, on April 15, 1991. During the interview, the Laingens discussed their experiences during the hostage crisis and their use of the yellow ribbon and the symbolic significance it acquired. The collection also contains photographs of the Laingens taken during this interview and photographs of yellow ribbon displays during the Persian Gulf War in 1991.
Biographical History
Penne (Penelope) Laingen is the wife of Bruce Laingen who was serving as the charge d'affaires of the United States Embassy in Tehran when Iranian student revolutionaries seized the Embassy on November 4, 1979, and held the staff hostage until January 20, 1981. A few days after Bruce was taken hostage, Penne Laingen hung a yellow ribbon around a tree in the yard of her Bethesda, Maryland home as a symbol of support for her husband and the other American hostages. She did this as a way to bolster her own strength and that of their three sons throughout the crisis.
Collection Concordance by Format
Manuscript Materials
15 folders Box 1 Folders 1-15
Sound Recordings
3 7-inch reel to reel audiotapes Box 2 SR01-SR03
3 audiocassettes Box 2 SR04-SR06
1 10-inch reel audiotape Box 2 SR07
Graphic Images
1 black-and-white contact sheet Box 1 PH001
28 black-and-white negatives Box 1 PH001, PH002
2 black-and-white prints Box 1 PH002, PH003
21 color prints Box 1 PH004-PH024
21 color negatives Box 1 PH004-PH024
11 color slides Box 1 PH002, PH025-PH034
2 color posters Map case GR01
Moving Images
1 videocassette (VHS), sound, color Box 2 MV01
Electronic Media
1 3.5-inch computer disk Box 1 CF01
Artifacts
5 novelty and display items Box 3 AR01-AR05
1 oilcloth ribbon Box 4 AR06
http://lccn.loc.gov/2004659952
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts
    - Finding Aid. 8 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - American Folklife Center and Laingens. February to July 1991. 8 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Santino, Jack. "Yellow Ribbons and Seasonal Flags: The Folk Assemblage of War." The Journal of American Folklore, 105, no. 415, (Winter 1992): 19-33. Drafts with comments and published version. 120 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Yellow Ribbon articles by Gerald Parsons, American Folklife Center reference specialist. 1981, 1991. 12 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Laingens Present Yellow Ribbon to LC." Library of Congress Gazette, 2, no. 28 (July 12, 1991): 3. (2 copies). 16 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Original Yellow Ribbon Given to LC." Library of Congress Information Bulletin, 50, no. 14, (July 15, 1991): 263. (5 copies). 50 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Parker, Barbara. "Penne Laingen's Wait." Washington Post, (Monday, December 10, 1979). 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Collected Articles: Significance of the Color Yellow. 1979-1981. 15 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Yellow Ribbon Acquisition Ceremony. Administrative Material. July 2, 1991. 42 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Yellow Ribbon Acquisition Ceremony. Press Coverage. July 2, 1991. 17 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Yellow Ribbons and "No Greater Love" (Humanitarian Organization). 1980-1990. 17 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Information regarding GR01 - Poster of Foshay Tower. 1981. 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      [Original poster located in Reading Room map case.]
    - Sound Recording Logs: SR01, SR02, SR03. Penne and Bruce Laingen interviewed on April 15, 1991, by Gerald Parsons. 13 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Sound Recording Transcript: SR01, SR02, SR03. Penne and Bruce Laingen interviewed on April 15, 1991, by Gerald Parsons. Transcript by Peggy Yocom. 10 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Moving Image Log: MV01. WRC Yellow Ribbon. Recording of the WRC, NBC News 4 nightly broadcast of the six o'clock news in Washington, DC featuring the Laingen yellow ribbon donation to the Library of Congress. July 2, 1991. 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II: Sound Recordings
  - Note: All contents have been removed from Box 2 and are shelved separately.
    - Penne and Bruce Laingen interviewed on April 15, 1991, by Gerald Parsons. Tape 1 of 3. One 7-inch reel recorded in stereo at 7.5 ips. (Box 2, Item SR01)
    - Penne and Bruce Laingen interviewed on April 15, 1991, by Gerald Parsons. Tape 2 of 3. One 7-inch reel recorded in stereo at 7.5 ips. (Box 2, Item SR02)
    - Penne and Bruce Laingen interviewed on April 15, 1991, by Gerald Parsons. Tape 3 of 3. One 7-inch reel recorded in stereo at 7.5 ips. (Box 2, Item SR03)
    - Recording of "Tie a Yellow Ribbon Round the Ole Oak Tree" sung by Tony Orlando and Dawn. Commercial recording dubbed on 1 audiocassette. (Box 2, Item SR04)
    - Recording of "She wore a yellow ribbon" sung by Mrs. Byron Coffin, Sr. of Alameda, CA. Recorded by Sidney Robertson Cowell in April 1939. Dubbed on 1 audiocassette. Accessible online at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/collafc.af000002. (Box 2, Item SR05)
    - Recordings of versions of "Tie a Yellow Ribbon Round the Ole Oak Tree" by Roger Williams and Andre Kostelanetz. Commercial recording dubbed on 1 audiocassette. (Box 2, Item SR06)
    - Recording of the donation of the original yellow ribbon to the Library of Congress in the Librarian's office, 6th Floor Madison Building, Washington, D.C. on July 2, 1991. One 10-inch sound tape reel recorded at 7.5 ips, 2 tracks. (Box 2, Item SR07)
- Series III: Graphic Images
    - Photograph: PH001 (contact sheet and negatives). (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Twenty-eight images of Penne and Bruce Laingen at their Bethesda, Maryland home during their interview with Gerald Parsons. April 15, 1991. One black-and-white contact sheet, 8 x 10 in. Five black-and-white negative strips with twenty-eight frames.
    - Photograph: PH002 (print, slide, and negative). (Box 1, Folder 17)
      An image of Bruce and Penne Laingen holding up the yellow ribbon around a tree in their Bethesda, Maryland yard. April 15, 1991. One black-and-white print, 8 x 10 in. One black-and-white negative strip with one frame. One color 35 mm slide of the same image.
    - Photograph: PH003 (print). (Box 1, Folder 18)
      An image of Penne Laingen presenting the original yellow ribbon to Librarian of Congress, James H. Billington. July 2, 1991. One black-andwhite print, 8 x 10 in.
    - Photographs: PH004 - PH024 (prints and negatives). (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Twenty-one images of yellow ribbons displayed in Maryland and Virginia during the Persian Gulf War, 1991. Photographer not known. Twenty-one color prints, 3 x 5 in. Six color negative strips with twenty-one frames.
    - Slides: PH025 - PH034 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Ten images of Penne and Bruce Laingen at their Bethesda, Maryland home during their interview with Gerald Parsons. April 15, 1991. Ten color slides, 35 mm.
    - Two copies of a color poster (Map Case, Item GR01)
      Foshay Tower at 821 Marquette Ave., Minneapolis, Hennepin County, Minnesota tied with an enormous yellow ribbon. 1981. Two color posters, 21 x 30 in. [See Reading Room Map Case]
- Series IV: Moving Images
  - Note: All contents have been removed from Box 2 and are shelved separately.
    - WRC Yellow Ribbon. Moving image of the WRC, NBC News 4 nightly broadcast of the six o'clock news in Washington, DC, featuring the Laingen yellow ribbon donation to the Library of Congress. July 2, 1991. One videocassette (VHS) in color with sound. See Folder 15 for the Moving Image Log. (Box 2, Item MV01)
- Series V: Artifacts
    - "God Bless America" pin featuring an American flag and a yellow ribbon. February 25, 1991. One novelty pin, 2 in. (Box 3, Item AR01)
    - "Yellow Ribbon Cocktail" sticks made in the shape of a ribbon. Undated. Eight novelty plastic sticks, 7 in. (Box 3, Item AR02)
    - "Free the Hostages" yellow ribbon pin framed by No Greater Love, a humanitarian organization that claims to have spearheaded the yellow ribbon campaign during the Iran hostage crisis. November 4, 1979 ­January 20, 1981. One framed item, 6 x 6 x 1.25 in. (Box 3, Item AR03)
    - "Tie a Yellow Ribbon Round the Ole Oak Tree" yellow ribbon display sign. Undated. One poster mounted on a plastic display stand, 8 x 10 in. (Box 3, Item AR04)
    - Mounted photograph of Bruce and Penne Laingen holding up their original yellow ribbon in the yard of their Bethesda, Maryland home. April 15, 1991. One color photograph mounted on a plastic display stand, 5.5 x 8 in. (Box 3, Item AR05)
    - The original yellow ribbon hung by Penne Laingen in honor of her husband, Bruce Laingen, while he was held hostage in Iran. 1979-1981. One oilcloth ribbon, 21 x 44 in. (Box 4, Item AR06)
- Series VI: Electronic Media
    - Computer Disk: CF01 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Administrative files related to the collection. One computer disk.